Dr. Truman Everett Ellis

CONTACT Information 1109 Lead Ave SW Albuquerque, NM 87102

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

Computational scientist with a background in aerospace engineering and an emphasis on fluid dynamics and shock physics. Exposure to a variety of simulation domains including solid mechanics, wave propagation, electromagnetics, heat transfer, and plasma physics. Experience running commercial CFD solvers as well as developing research codes for a wide range of flow domains. Well developed programming and development skills with an affinity for clean, elegant solutions. Comfortable with both spoken and written communication skills with experience working in a team environment as well as individually.

Professional Experience

Postdoctoral Scientist - Plasma Physics

2016 to present

Phone: +1-512-814-8304

Email: teellis@sandia.gov

Electromagnetic Theory Group,

Sandia National Laboratory

- Developing highly scalable plasma physics simulations using the Trilinos Project.
- Contributing to a test harness for stochastic simulation codes using a new theory of stochastic Richardson extrapolation implemented in Python.
- Involvement with experimental studies of electro-magnetic pulses and analysis of data collected.

Graduate Research Assistant – Stabilized Finite Elements

2010 to 2016

Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences,

University of Texas at Austin

- Developed discontinuous Petrov-Galerkin finite element methods for fluid flow applications.
- Contributed significantly to Camellia, a parallel C++ library built on Trilinos for rapid development of DPG problem formulations.
- Wrote bridge code to enable output in VTK and HDF5 formats.
- Added support for space-time parabolic problems.
- Implemented an exactly conservative formulation of DPG through Lagrange multipliers.
- Contributed to open source libMesh finite element library.

Graduate Student Researcher - Shock Hydrocodes

2008 to 2013

Institute for Scientific Computing Research,

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

- Worked in a small research group developing advanced finite element discretization methods for Lagrangian hydrodynamics.
- Improved staggered grid hydro algorithms in multi-material Arbitrary Lagrangian Eulerian codes.
- Wrote a prototype code in Matlab to explore the benefits of using high order finite element pairs.
- Extended Blast, the next iteration object oriented C++ shock physics code to axisymmetric problems.
- Implemented a smoothness indicator to isolate artificial viscosity to shocked and underresolved flow regions.
- Developed a Python-scriptable 2D plotting tool to interface with the research code.
- Contributed to open source MFEM finite element library.

 ${\bf Undergraduate~Student~Researcher} - {\it Shock~Tube~Experiments}$

Summer 2007

Research Experience for Undergraduates, Aerospace Engineering,

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

• Compressible Flows in Geological Applications - Designed a series of experiments and set up a lab to study the Mount St. Helens lateral blast.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas, Austin

GPA: 3.92

Ph.D., Computational Science Engineering and Mathematics, April 2016

- Thesis Topic: Space-time Discontinuous Petrov-Galerkin Finite Elements for Transient Computational Fluid Dynamics
- Advisors: Leszek Demkowicz, Robert Moser

California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo

GPA: 3.93

M.S., Aerospace Engineering, June 2010

- Thesis Topic: High Order Finite Elements for Lagrangian Computational Fluid Dynamics
- Advisors: Tzanio Kolev, Robert Rieben, Faysal Kolkailah
- Summa cum Laude, With Highest Honors in Engineering

B.S., Aerospace Engineering, June 2010

- Aeronautics specialization
- Summa cum Laude, With Highest Honors in Engineering

REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

T.E. Ellis, J. Chan, and L. Demkowicz (2016),

Robust DPG Methods for Transient Convection-Diffusion. Lecture Notes in Computational Science and Engineering, doi:10.1007/978-3-319-41640-3_6

T.E. Ellis, and L. Demkowicz (2014),

Locally Conservative Discontinuous Petrov-Galerkin Finite Elements for Fluid Problems.

Computers & Mathematics with Applications, doi:10.1016/j.camwa.2014.07.005

V. Dobrev, T.E. Ellis, Tz. Kolev and R. Rieben (2012),

High-order Curvilinear Finite Elements for Axisymmetric Lagrangian Hydrodynamics.

Computers & Fluids, doi:10.1016/j.compfluid.2012.06.004

V. Dobrev, T.E. Ellis, Tz. Kolev and R. Rieben (2011), Curvilinear Finite Elements for Lagrangian Hydrodynamics. International Journal for Numerical Methods in Fluids, doi:10.1002/fld.2366

SOFTWARE SKILLS Computer Programming:

• C++, Python, Lua, MATLAB, Mathematica, and others

Scientific Computing Libraries:

• Trilinos, FEniCS, libMesh, MFEM, NumPy, SciPy, and others

CFD / Engineering Software:

• Fluent, Gambit, SolidWorks, Pro/ENGINEER, and others

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Computational fluid dynamics, shock physics, multi-phase flows, turbulence modeling, finite element methods, Lagrangian hydrocodes, computational plasma dynamics, magnetohydrodynamics, computational mechanics

AWARDS

- Computational Applied Math Fellow University of Texas
- Graduated Summa cum Laude Cal Poly
- President's Honors List Cal Poly 2005 2007
- $\bullet\,$ Dean's List Cal Poly 2005 2008
- Litton Industries in Engineering Scholarship Cal Poly 2007 2008
- Accenture Outstanding AERO Award Cal Poly 2007
- Reinhold Aerospace Engineering Scholarship Cal Poly 2007